Finding Aid for the Ferdinand Praeger Collection of Scores, circa 1829-1891
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Ferdinand Praeger Collection of Scores, circa 1829-1891
Mus. Arc. 46
Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891
17 boxes ( 484 items )
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
This is the largest collection of Ferdinand Praeger's manuscripts in the world, consisting of approximately 480 works. The majority of the works are for piano, but the collection also includes chamber music for strings, large ensemble works, vocal works, and sketches. The dated works range from 1829-1891, but many works are undated.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Purchased in London by James Coover, Summer 1984.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
Selected scores and documents in the collection have been digitized. Links to digital copies are provided in the container list.
Biographical Note
Ferdinand Praeger was born in Leipzig on January 22, 1815, to a Dutch father and an English mother. As a child, he studied cello, piano, and violin. His father, Heinrich Aloys Praeger (1783-1854) worked as a musician, composer, and conductor. From 1815-1821, he conducted a small traveling opera company called the Joseph Seconda German Opera Company.
In 1831, at the age of 16, Praeger became a music teacher at The Hague and continued to study piano, violin, and composition. He moved to London in 1834, working as a teacher and traveling to give piano recitals, many of which included his own works. Praeger became the London correspondent for Robert Schumann's music journal, Neue Zeitschrift für Musik, in 1842. His contributions included highlights of London musical events, reviews of performances, and general discussions about current musical topics. Praeger held this position until 1890, the year before his death.
Praeger's compositions were performed in cities across Europe, including Paris, Leipzig, Berlin, Hamburg, and Meiningen. In London, his orchestral works were performed in private home concerts as well as larger venues, such as the Crystal Palace. On July 10, 1879, Praeger's students organized and presented a concert of his compositions in his honor.
Praeger is perhaps best known today for his connection with Richard Wagner. Wagner stayed with Praeger during a trip to London and the two apparently remained close friends. Following Wagner's death, Praeger wrote the book Wagner, as I Knew Him, which quickly became controversial and was pulled from publication. Wagner followers disputed the book, claiming that Praeger exaggerated his role in Wagner's life and portrayed Wagner in a negative way. Praeger's other literary contributions include the unpublished textbook, Guide Pratique pour la Composition avec des Illustrations Originales, and a translation of Emil Naumann's Illustrated History of Music from 1886.
Little is known about Praeger's family. He married a French woman named Leonie around 1850. His first son, Henry, was born a year later. In 1855, they had another son named Richard Wagner Praeger, to whom Richard Wagner was godfather; but he is not known to have lived to adulthood.
Ferdinand Praeger died on September 2, 1891, in London.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 484 items, all but a few of which are manuscript scores. The majority of the works are for piano, but the collection also includes chamber music for strings, large ensemble works, vocal works, and sketches. The dated works range from 1829-1891, but many works are undated. A small number of documents are also included in the collection. This is the largest collection of Praeger's musical manuscripts in the world, and these works have not been included in any previous writings or works lists related to Praeger. Nearly all the scores are in Praeger's own hand.
The manuscripts are in varying conditions. Some are in very good condition, considering their age, while others are close to disintegration. Some pieces have become stuck together, and in some cases, only bits of one page are stuck to another, obscuring the music. These pieces have been scanned digitally to create a composite image of the full page wherever possible, however, some information is inevitably lost.
Praeger used paper inserts to correct or alter his manuscripts. These are small pieces of paper glued over the original passage to replace it with different music. Over time, many of these inserts have become loose or detached from the manuscripts. Effort was made to match the loose inserts to their original places and mark them with measure numbers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series:
I. Keyboard works
II. Chamber works with piano
III. String chamber works
IV. Large ensemble works
V. Vocal works
VI. Sketches and fragments
VII. Documents
Container List
- Keyboard works, 1837-1891, I.; Item 001-369
  Arranged into four subseries:
  A. Piano
  B. Piano four hands
  C. Organ
  D. Piano reductions
  - Piano, 1837-1891, A.; Item 001-332
    Some of the piano sonatas indicate a key area, but not the mode. These works begin in the minor mode and end in the major mode of that key.
    Arranged alphabetically by uniform title.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Adagios, piano, C major (1891) Adagio [in C major] / 1891, [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 001)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Dedication in German at bottom of p. [1]: "To Julius, 16 April 1891". Corrections on insert pasted on p. [1]. Paper torn; bottom right corner missing.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Adagios, piano, E♭ major Adagio [in E flat major] / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 38 cm. (Box 1, Item 002)
      For piano. Title from initial tempo marking. Holograph (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Adagios, piano, E♭ major (1890) Adagio [in E flat major], 1890, [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 003)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 9/5 90. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1, 3].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Adagios, piano, F♯ minor Adagio [in F sharp minor] / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 004)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Bottom of p. 1-2 partially missing.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Adagio & allegro agitato, piano Adagio & allegro agitato / 1888-1891, 3, 6 p. of ms. music; 31 cm.; Alternate title: Adagio und allegro agitato Alternate title: Adagio and allegro agitato (Box 1, Item 005)
      For piano. Cover title. Adagio caption: "17th Aug 88"; Allegro agitato caption: "Jan. 1891". Holograph (Ink). Sections are numbered separately. Corrections on insert pasted on p. 4 of Allegro agitato.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Adagio & allegro con fuoco, piano Adagio & allegro con fuoco / 1891, [2], 4 p. of ms. music; 31 cm.; Alternate title: Adagio und allegro con fuoco Alternate title: Adagio and allegro con fuoco (Box 1, Item 006)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 8/4 91.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Adagio religioso / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 007)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Album leaf / 1884, [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 008)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). "Composed for Miss Maggie Oakey, April 1884"--Caption. Corrections on inserts pasted on both pages. Possibly incomplete.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Albumblatt, piano, E?♭ major Album leaf [in E flat major] / 1888, [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 009)
      For piano. Caption title. Additional title in caption indecipherable. Holograph (Ink); 51 measures. Caption: May 88. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Albumblatt, Albumblatt / 1888, [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 010)
      For piano. Cover title. Cover: Juni 1888. Holograph (Ink); 50 measures.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Allegrettos, piano, A♭ major Allegretto [in A flat major] / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 011)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Allegrettos, piano, G minor Allegretto [in G minor] / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 012)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Allegretto grazioso / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 013)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Allegro maestoso, piano, E♭ major Allegro maestoso [in E flat major] / 1891, [5] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 014)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 21/1 91.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Allegro maestoso, piano, D major Allegro maestoso [in D major] / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 015)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Allegretto scherzando, piano Allegretto scherzando / [18--], [6] p. of ms. music; 29 cm. (Box 1, Item 016)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Alte litanei / [18--], 1 p. of ms. music; 29 cm. (Box 1, Item 017)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Ancien menuet [in G major] / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 018)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Ancient maypole dance / [18--], 3 p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 019)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Ancient minuet [in A minor] / 1888, 1 p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 020)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 11/12 88.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Andantes, piano, A minor Andante [in A minor] / 1890, [2] p. of ms. music; 30 cm. (Box 1, Item 021)
      For piano. Title from initial tempo marking. Holograph (Ink). "Composed for & dedicated to H.P. Dickenson Esqr."--Caption Caption: 17/6 .90.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Andantes, piano, E♭ major Andante [in E flat major] / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 022)
      For piano. Title from initial tempo marking. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted throughout.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Andante & allegro, piano, G major Andante & allegro / 1890, [6], 3 p. of ms. music; 31 cm.; Alternate title: Andante und allegro Alternate title: Andante and allegro (Box 1, Item 023)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). End of Andante (p. [5]): Nov. 1, 1890. Final two measures of Allegro corrected on insert.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Andantino, piano, C major Andantino / [18--], [7] p. of ms. music; 30 cm. (Box 1, Item 024)
      For piano. Title from initial tempo marking. Holograph (Ink), with additional markings in pencil. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 L'aveu / [18--], 5 p. of ms. music; 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 025)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. 3-4.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Ballet Louis XIV Ballet Louis XIV: air historique / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 34 cm.; Alternate title: Air historique Alternate title: Ballet Louis Quatorzième (Box 1, Item 026)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on both pages.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Barcarolles, piano, G major Barcarole [in G major] / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Item 027)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1-3].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Barcarolles, piano, G minor Barcarole [in G minor] / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 028)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 1, Bohemian air Bohemian air: no. 1 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 029)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Paper in poor condition, with holes and tears. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1]. "13 Bohemian airs &c.: Russian, Arabic, Hungarian &c."--Additional title card with printer name W. Straker, Printer, Ludgate Hill and Liverpool Street.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 2, Chant bohémien Chant bohémien: no. 2 of the Bohemian airs / [18--], [6] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 030)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1, 2, 5, 6].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 3, Böhmischer Bauernsang Böhmischer Bauernsang: no. 3 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 031)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 4, Ungarisch Ungarisch: no. 4 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], [5] p. of ms. music; 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 032)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1-5]; loose insert in envelope.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 5, Marche hongroise Marche hongroise: no. 5 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], 4 p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 033)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 6, Air hongrois Air hongrois: no. 6 of the Bohemian airs &c. / 1885, [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 034)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: Aug. 1885. Piece missing from bottom right of page. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 7, Air hongrois Air hongrois: no. 7 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 035)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 8, Ungarisch Ungarisch: no. 8 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 036)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 9, Polnische Lieder Polnische Lieder: no. 9 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 037)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1, 3].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 10, Chanson slave Chanson slave: no. 10 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], 6 p. of ms. music; 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 038)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. 3, 5.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 10, Russiche Lieder Russiche Lieder: Slavonic melodies / 1881, [7] p. of ms. music; 35 cm.; Alternate title: Slavonic melodies (Box 1, Item 039)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). At head of cover: No. 10 of the Bohemian airs &c.; number seems to have been changed, possibly from 14. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [4].
      Contents: 1. Moderato ("8 August 1881") -- 2. Un poco moderato -- 3. Moderato ("8 Aug 1881") -- No. 4. Allegretto ("9 Aug 1881") -- 8. Moderato -- No. 9. Allegretto animato -- No. 10. Allegretto -- No. 11. Moderato.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 11, Slavonic ditties Slavonic ditties: Russiche Lieder: no. 11 of the Bohemian airs &c. / 1881, [4] p. of ms. music; 35 cm.; Alternate title: Russiche Lieder (Box 1, Item 040)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 19 Sept. 1881.
      Contents: No. 1. Moderato -- No. 2. Presto -- No. 3. Moderato -- No. 4. Moderato -- No. 5. Moderato -- No. 6. Allegro moderato -- No. 7. Andantino.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 12, Savoyardenlied Savoyardenlied: no. 12 of the Bohemian airs &c. / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 041)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections in manuscript pasted on p. [1].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bohemian airs. No. 13, Arabian melody Arabian melody: no. 13 of the Bohemian airs &c. / 1881, [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm.; Alternate title: Added title in caption: Extent of a third (Box 1, Item 042)
      Contents: No. 1. Moderato ("30 July 1881") -- No. 2. Lento: on the tetrachord ("31st") -- No. 3. Animato (31st July) -- No. 4 -- No. 5. Lento -- No. 6. Lento.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Bourrées, piano, E minor Bourrée / 1889, [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 043)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 12 Nov. 89. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Capriccios, piano, A major Capriccio pour le pianoforte [in A major] / [18--], [7] p. of ms. music; 29 cm. (Box 2, Item 044)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink) with additions in pencil. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [2].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Capriccios, piano, G major Capriccio [in G major] / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 29 cm. (Box 2, Item 045)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [2].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Cerisette / [1880], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 046)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Chanson a boire / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 24 x 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 047)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Contains instructions for the engraver.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Chanson d'autrefois La chanson d'autrefois, or the old song: piano / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm.; Alternate title: Chanson d'autrefois Alternate title: Old song (Box 2, Item 048)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Chanson historique / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 049)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Chant d'amour / 1887, [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 050)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 27 July 1887; at end of score: 30 July.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Chant guerrier / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 051)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Character sketches from novels / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 052)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Musical portraits of characters in the novel John Halifax, Gentleman by Dinah Maria Mulock Craik (London: Hurst and Blackett, 1856).
      Contents: John Halifax -- Ursula -- Abel Fletcher -- Abel's son Phineas -- The blind child Muriel.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Con vivasità / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 053)
      For piano. Title from initial tempo-expression marking. Holograph (Ink). Bottom of p. [2] contains instructions for engraving.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Danse moresque / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 054)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 2 Daydream no. 2 / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 28 cm. (Box 2, Item 055)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). "To his friend B.L. Mosely"--Caption.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 3 Daydreams no. 3 / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 056)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 4 Daydreams no. 4 / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 057)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink) with caption in pencil. "Composed & dedicated to J.A. Edwards Esqr."--Caption.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 6 Daydreams no. 6 / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 058)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 7 Daydream no. 7 / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 059)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 8 Daydreams no. 8 / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 060)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). At head of title: [indecipherable] Träume.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 9 Daydream no. 9 / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 061)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 10 Daydreams no. 10: Wache Träume / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm.; Alternate title: Wache Träume (Box 2, Item 062)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Correction on insert pasted on p. [1].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 11 Daydreams no. 11: Es dur / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 063)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Subtitle on cover: [indecipherable] Träume.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 12 Daydreams no. 12 / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 064)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Subtitle in caption: [indecipherable] und Glück.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 13 Day-dreams no. 13 / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm.; Alternate title: Daydreams no. 13 (Box 2, Item 065)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [3].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 14 Day-dream no. 14: Zu Tode betrübt / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm.; Alternate title: Daydream no. 14 Alternate title: Zu Tode betrübt (Box 2, Item 066)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 16 Daydream no. 16 / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 067)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 17 Daydream no. 17 / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 068)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Subtitle in caption: [indecipherable] Träume. Correction on insert pasted on p. [2].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 18 Daydreams no. 18: Traumbildnis / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 28 cm.; Alternate title: Traumbildnis (Box 2, Item 069)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, no. 19 Daydream no. 19 / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 070)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1-2].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, C major Daydreams no. [blank]: in C major / 1888, [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 071)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: Nov. 4 88; on cover: Nov. 88.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, C minor (1889, March) Daydreams [in C minor], 1889, [4] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 072)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: March 89.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, C minor, (1889, April) Daydreams: C minor, 1889, [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 073)
      For piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 1 April 1889. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, E♭ major Day dreams [in E flat major] / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 30 cm. (Box 2, Item 074)
      For piano. Caption title. Manuscript (Reproduction).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, F minor Daydreams [in F minor] / [18--], [4] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 075)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Daydreams, piano, F minor (Moderato) Daydreams [in F minor, Moderato] / [18--], [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 076)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Initial tempo marking: Moderato.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Dirge, piano, F minor A dirge [in F minor] / 1889, [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 077)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 24/2 89.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Dirge, piano, A minor Dirge [in A minor] / 1889, [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 078)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 3 May 89; third system: 4 May.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Dodlinette / [18--], [2] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Item 079)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891 Elegy, piano, G minor Elegy / 1889, [2] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Item 080)
      For piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 30/12 88; top of p. [2]: 6 Jan 89.